Foreign
welcome to three Angels Media
International lesson
discussion.
We excited to share
this wonderful
lesson of daily living
as we engage
with you.
I am your host
Pastor John Wako
and I have my co host here,
Pastor James.
It's exciting to be with
you again.
Welcome to 3AMI 3
Angels Media International.
We are excited to have our
team members with us
today as we discuss
a lesson caption the problem
of evil I have Elder
Babalola here with us.
We're happy to meet you.
God bless you as you listen.
Amen.
And we also have
Dr.
Esther.
Welcome everyone.
May you be blessed as we
study together.
Amen.
The problem of evil
is a
topic that
is
very
somewhat
not joyous
at the same time
not
it's something that all of
us have experienced.
But the Lord will guide us
as we discuss
and as we encourage one another.
Let us sing.
My Jesus, I love
you.
I love
me.
I know
that
my
gracious,
My
Savior,
I love
the my
Jesus.
Father, we have come to you
once again
to learn at your feet
we come as empty
as we are.
Father, please fill us today.
Though sinful we are,
but we are here before you
to be cleansed.
Cleanse us, Forgive our
sins that the
meditations of our heart
and the words of our
mouth may be acceptable unto
you today.
Oh Lord, minister to our
listeners at home home and
let us all be blessed in
Jesus name.
Amen.
The problem of
evil and God will
wipe away.
That's a very encouraging
part.
If you have gone through
evil,
if you know someone
who are going through evil,
injustice, pain,
sickness, disease,
death of loved ones,
premature death,
tragic death,
cancer.
Things that has happened
in our
history, in our human experience
that are
painful.
We are told in
Revelation 21, verse
4 that
God will
wipe away every tear
from our eyes.
There shall be no more death.
That is the highest
point of disappointment
and evil in human
history.
Even in the
history of God's creation.
Even in in the
entire both
in heaven and earth.
Death is not something that
God look forward to, that
God loves because originally
it was not his intention.
So we are consoled to know
that God will wipe
away every
fear from our
eyes.
There shall be no more death,
nor sorrow.
No more crying, no
more pain, no more disease,
no more sicknesses,
no more poverty,
starvation, no more
injustice.
There shall be no more pain
for the former things
have passed
away.
Perhaps the greatest problem
facing the entire human
race today, I wouldn't just
say Christian religion, the
entire human race, the entire
human experience is
this problem of
evil.
I'm sure you have experienced
pain, you have
experienced evil.
Have Experienced loss.
You have experience
something that you know,
this one is not in the plan
of God for me.
So that is one of the greatest
problem we.
We each face today.
And many times, how do
we reconcile this with the
fact that we know
that God is
perfectly good?
And this God is so
perfect, he's so loving,
he's so.
He cares about us so much,
and yet
we live in a
world that is filled
with evil.
So many people,
it becomes so difficult for
them to come to terms.
If God is all
good, as we say
he is,
and all powerful,
then that question,
why evil?
Why is there so much evil
in our world?
Why is there so much
pain and disease and
poverty?
Why are so much
trouble?
Why is it that these troubles
have become part of our human
experience?
And many people, you know,
keep facing these
things and they keep asking,
where is the love of God?
So to many minds, the
origin of sin and the reason
for its existence actually
a source of great perplexity.
I know many people
that because of
the situation of our
world, has said there is
no God.
I was walking
in Norway many
years ago, actually
2004, and I met
someone who was challenging me.
He said, can you see my hands
are walking?
He lifted his hands.
He said, this hand is walking.
He said.
He said, can you see my.
Can you see this mansion?
He has a very big house.
He said, which God?
This is my.
The works of my hand.
I did it.
I was just looking at the
man because he's still breathing.
If God takes away the air,
he realized that they are sick.
Many years ago, I was walking
here and also met a
man who
was in Rwanda
in 1994.
He was a
pastor.
He finished
theology school
here in the United States
and moved over.
Actually graduated from La
Sierra University and moved
over to Rwanda.
And he was there
in that genocide.
So he came
back and
said, there is no more God.
Become an atheist from
pastor and I
engage him.
You know, the most difficult
person is someone who's been
through, who already knows
everything through theology.
What are you going to pull?
What are you going to.
So many people, because of
the situation of the world,
when they face a
certain level of evil,
they begin to question
our rationale.
But the good news
is that
despite the evil
that exists in our world,
we have a God
who has infinite
love, infinite
power and infinite wisdom.
Unfortunately, sometimes
he doesn't use that
power always.
That is the truth.
God uses more of
love and
mercy and grace than he
utilizes his
sovereign power.
Many of us have been in
situations where we have
asked this question, how
long O Lord,
how long, O Lord?
In fact, I
change it here to say because
of the domineering and
enduring presence of
evil.
There are times we have been
in situations where
we begin to ask God, is this
gonna end?
How long?
How long is this going to be?
So the problem of evil is real.
It is real, and it's
a very big problem that puts
a lot of question marks on
the goodness of
God.
Can we
please look at
job 30, verse
26?
So I looked for good,
but evil
came instead.
My heart is
troubled and
restless.
Days of suffering
torment me.
Days of.
Because Job was in that
situation where he was like,
how long,
God, are you sure this
is going to end?
How long is this going to be?
The night has become
so long and the
daybreak was not there.
And we look at again
Jeremiah, the Prophet in
12:1.
He answered that question
in a way righteous
are you, O Lord,
when I plead with
you, yet
let me talk
with you about your
judgment.
Why does the way of
the wicked
prosper?
Why are those
happy who deal
so
treacherously?
And sometimes
honestly, some of
these treacherous
people seem to be prospering
there, sir.
Yeah. What experience do you want to share?
Well,
evil people
prosper a lot.
A lot.
You see somebody who doesn't know God.
You see somebody who
even speak bad of
God, so disrespectful to
God, but in his
business he's making
waves.
Like I started an example
before.
A very popular person that
anybody who hears this will
know the person right away.
Yes.
We're talking, say.
Well, if you say there is heaven.
Yes.
If you say there is paradise,
he doesn't believe it.
But if it exists,
I would like to.
Yeah. It won't be bad to visit.
It's okay.
But it's okay.
And he's the richest
person in the world.
So that person,
God allowed him to make his way.
God gave him the intelligence.
God prospered him.
God blessed everything he
touched.
Yet he's not
religious.
He doesn't believe that you
need any special connection
with any power
anywhere.
Yes.
So when you look at that
and you that you are worshiping
God day and night.
Yes.
You are not lazy in your
office, in your job.
Yes.
You went to school, yet you
don't see you are not really making it.
That's right.
Then you query God, God,
what is happening?
You asked me to worship,
I'm doing it.
But we need to know
that the same Bible says
we should not envy that.
Then we should not
bother to gather our
treasure in this
earth, because our
reward is in heaven.
Because what does
it prosper in man who
gains all this word.
And yet.
So it's better to
keep focusing on
the goal.
And that is heaven.
All right, Dr.
Esther.
Yeah, yeah.
So I like that
question you asked, Pastor.
Why do
the wicked ones seem to
prosper, even sometimes more
than the so called Christian?
Yes, but there's something
that Job
found out.
God let Job know that not
everything, there's not.
- It's
not everything that he can understand.
Same thing with us.
It's not everything that
we are going to understand.
There are some things only
best known to God.
And just like
eventually all of these
riches of this world is going
to come to an end, it's going
to turn to nothing.
Heaven is the goal.
So once you have at the back of
your mind that heaven
is the goal, you will not
be influenced or
confused by the
wicked being
prospering.
And we should not envy
them when they are prospering
like that because God of
justice will still bring
justice upon the wicked
eventually.
Amen.
And Dr.
Jail, where
is God when evil
occurs?
Why do you think
God is all
this powerful?
Why still evil in the world?
God is where he was when
he allowed Jesus to
crucify,
is where he was when
Jesus said,
father, why
hast thou forsaken?
He's still on the truth.
And that is why there are
some things
he did not understand.
And may I quickly add
that God is not the author
of evil.
God did not bring evil.
As we study this lesson,
for that that we unravel,
we see, but God
did not bring about
evil.
It is disobedience that led to evil.
And God did not cause
disobedience.
That's right.
All right, so
the question now is, why
do the righteous
suffer?
If God is a good
God, he created a good world.
Where is he
when in quote, the
righteous are suffering and
the wicked are
prospering.
They are having their way.
They are materially speaking,
things are working well for them.
And you who prays to
this God all the time,
fast, who goes
to church, who is
committed,
yet things are not
going well
for you?
Well, God is
touched.
That's why I raised that
question.
God is touched by
human suffering
and the evils that
we each experience along the way.
The question that is
begging for answers
will be, have each and every
one of us here, who among
us here has an experience
level?
Who among us having experience
level all
the things we pray for, does
it come to pass?
Do we get all that we
pray for?
God is touched by human
suffering.
God also
grieves
at each of
Our loss
at each of our pain, the
death of our loved ones,
the injustices that we
face, the
evil that we experience
in our world today persists.
Because God is not the
only one with
power of
choice.
That is the answer.
Satan also has the
power of choice, and he uses it.
The gracious
also has the
power of choice as well.
So Satan, as well as
human beings can choose
too, to
utilize their power of choice
to inflict pain
on us,
to also thwart
the plan of God.
I know many people that will
be shocking to them.
Does it mean.
Yes.
The plan of God does not
always materialize the way
he envisions it.
God also get
frustrated
because he doesn't use his
mighty power all the time.
Instead, he
leads us through our
power of choice,
through our free will
to decide.
So when you look at
Matthew 27,
verse 42, Jesus
also faced the
harshest experience.
Because of evil,
because of our sins.
He had to ask
God, where are you?
Just like all of us,
at a particular time in our
life, as usual, he
has to feel the
abandonment of the
absence of God
to intervene at the most
painful time in his
human and divine experience.
So God also suffers.
You believe that?
Yes, God also
suffers.
Do you know what it took
God to watch?
His son.
Ellen White said that God
couldn't even look at
him.
God couldn't look at his
face.
And Jesus even called,
reached out to God and said,
are you still there?
God was there.
But at that time, the
weight of
seeing the
load and everything was
on Jesus.
And he has to go through
the way of the cross.
That's something that we
cannot say.
We have all the answers
because it's too deep for
us to comprehend.
So we are called to choose
wisely, to make the best
use of our choices,
to choose wisely and to stand
by God, to partner with
God, to work with
him and to
create meaningful
and impactful and rewarding
experiences devoid of
evil.
Because many times people
stay in this how long?
Experience because of
human choices, because
people are inflicting
pain.
We've seen injustices
in some way.
We've seen people that use
their pen to just
sign something
and they have just signed
to kill an innocent man.
We've seen people that spend
27 years,
30 years in prison
and the police knew
that they were not the one
that committed the crime.
But they have to close the case.
The police is bribed,
the judge was bribed.
They had to do something
to cover someone.
And an innocent man was
sent to jail
for 30 years.
In fact, we've seen many
People sent to the death
row.
That means they actually
got killed.
They got executed for a
crime that they did not
commit.
So these are things that happen.
And many times
there are many of these things
that we don't have all the answers.
We cannot say
we know why this has happened.
Now let us look at Job.
Job was in this experience
because many times we seem
to, you know, behave like we
have all the answers to some
things, all the things that happen.
Let us see.
Job 38,
verse 1 through 12.
Then the Lord spoke to Job
out of the storm.
He said, who is
this that obscures my
plans with words
without knowledge?
Brace yourself like a man.
I will question you, and
you shall answer me.
Where were you when I laid
the earth's foundation?
Tell me if you understand,
who marked off its
dimensions?
Surely you know
who stretched a
measuring line across
it On.
On what were its footings set?
Or who laid its
cornerstone while the
Morningstar sang together
and all the angels shouted
for joy?
Who shut up the see
behind doors when it burst
forth from the room?
When I made the clouds its
garment and wrapped it in.
Wrapped it in thick
darkness When I fixed
limits for it and set its
doors and bars in
place When I
said, this far you may
come and no further.
Here is where your proud
waves ought.
Have you ever given orders
to the money or shown
the dawn its place?
That's it, all right.
So the question God was posing
to Job here is something
that all of us should ponder
on.
Were you there when I laid
the foundation of the earth?
Do you know the one who commands
day?
And there is daybreak.
Can you explain how it
happens?
And when it's night, okay,
it's night.
It's something that was shocking
to me the first time I went
to Europe,
precisely in Norway,
that during
some summer times,
you just have to go to bed
because it's
daybreak all
through is
shocking.
Like by
1:00am in the morning,
by 12 midnight,
1:00am,
2:00am it's
like, wow.
It's just that everywhere
is very white.
Everybody's sleeping now.
There's no.
You know everywhere is.
You know, you're hearing
the birds, the
crickets, you know.
So there is someone who makes
it to go dark.
And it's night,
right?
And then there's someone
who commands day to come.
There are someone who says,
the ocean.
This is where you start
that, you know.
And many times when the ocean
overflows, you see the
disaster that comes.
So God is trying to tell
us here,
even in our human experience,
that there are some things
we cannot comprehend.
The End of history.
We come with the triumph
of love over
evil.
There is someone who knows
what he's doing, even
though it may be very, very
difficult for us to
comprehend some
of the things he's doing.
Sometimes let us
also know that many of the
things that happen is not
because of our sin.
It's not because of what
our parents did.
It's not because of,
you know, something that
we didn't do.
It's just that there are
so many other actors.
There are principalities
and powers
that are working
night and day.
Although it is very difficult,
we have to learn to trust
God in these times
we are in the dark, we don't
have all the details.
And that's why it's very
difficult to
trust.
When you are in the dark,
you don't have all the details.
So God is saying, learn
to trust me in those difficult
times, even
when it is very difficult
for you to trust, learn to
give me praise.
And that's another thing
that I have actually experienced
my personal journey, my personal life.
When you're in a difficult
situation, you start praising God.
It works.
So let us understand
that
we have
been given
immense power
and we have to learn to
use those power
of choice wisely.
As I stated before,
someone just signed a signature
and someone's contract is
unjustly ended.
Someone signs a signature
and someone
is going to spend the rest
of their years,
20 years, 10 years in
jail.
Someone is bribed.
You know, there are so many
angles to this, and
that is because of this
problem of evil.
So God is calling us to
go into partnership with
him as we make our choices,
as we touch people, and as
we impart their
lives in those worldwe stay
with us.
Don't go away.
When we return,
we will continue this conversation.
Thank you.
Welcome back.
There's something called
skeptical.
A theist is somebody
who believes in God.
That's where we get atheists
for those who do not believe
in God.
So the skeptical
theist is
the one who believes
that God has good
reasons for acting
the way he does.
But given our limited
knowledge that
we shouldn't expect to be
in a position
to know
all the reasons why the
things that happen happen.
And if we're
able to become skeptical
theist, it will
help us
to trust God more,
knowing that
our knowledge is limited.
How can you explain
that a woman
got married?
According to her, as
a virgin
for 14 years
they looked for a child
she couldn't conceive.
And after 14 years
she gets a child.
And then the second child
comes 13 years
later.
So she gets a son,
27 years later,
she rejoices.
Now she has a daughter and
a son,
only to bury this
son 25 years later.
Yeah.
And that is my mother's story.
How can you explain this?
What, are you going to justify
this?
The only justification
is that we are in a world
of evil.
That's right, because it
has nothing to do
with God.
When my brother died,
I prayed for God to
resurrect him.
Because
I know that God
could resurrect him if he
wanted to.
I even went to the mortuary
and told them to bring him
out, that I want to pray
on his corpse.
And after a long process,
they brought him out.
Said, God, I am here now.
Been praying to you from America.
But I'm here in this mortuary
in Aba.
Please wake this my
brother.
But God did it.
And we buried him.
But God
sees our pain and
he never leaves us
alone.
And while we were
mourning,
God made it possible
that his wife that was
pregnant gave
birth safely
to his son.
That is his replica.
So as we look back
at him will
be eight
years this year.
We still have something to
thank God for.
I'm telling this story to
somebody who may be going
through something out there,
and they may think that you
are alone.
Some devout Christians like
me have been through
stuff.
But God gives
us the grace
to know
that there is hope
after this world of sin,
that there will be resurrection,
when we are going to see
our loved ones.
That instead of staying and
brooding
on all the evils that
happen every day,
that we should
realize the limited
knowledge we have and
trust God more because he
is the one that has all the answers.
That's true.
And when I was reading through
EV White's
writings.
Excuse me.
And she said that even
in heaven, there
are some things we would
not understand.
Because even in heaven, we
will still still be human
beings that will not be God.
A lot of things we will understand,
but not everything.
Because even in heaven, we
will not turn into God.
We are still going to be
human beings.
That was when I rested my case.
I said, you know what?
I'm a human being.
I'm grateful to be
here to experience this
grace and mercy from an
almighty God.
And I will leave
him to be God
while I remain
the human being.
So David in Psalm
was wondering, because
he was a king,
and he was wondering
why kings
that do a lot of
evil, that do
not fear God,
that do everything
but what God wants them to do.
- Prospering.
- Yeah.
In fact, he was specific.
Why are they amassing
wealth, Lord,
why we have to struggle.
Why are they amassing wealth
when they are doing the wrong thing?
But the
answer is
there that
he got that answer when he
step, when he
focused his
attention to the sanctuary
of God and that was when he got the answer.
He said the answer was
found the sanctuary of God.
Because you have to shift
your focus
to God to
really get the answers.
Then God will speak to you
and tell you that
this is why
I'm doing what I'm doing.
There is peace in this.
And sometimes you may not
still get all the answers,
but we just have to shift
our focus
from trying to
envy the wicked
to focusing on
God and appreciating
him for being our God.
And one
thing as I studied it, that
will help us,
apart from being a skeptical
theist of allowing God
be God
and knowing that we still
have limited knowledge, is
to ask yourself,
why am I serving God?
Am I serving God
because I want to amass wealth
or am I serving God because
I'm responding
to his love for me?
The reason why you're serving
God will determine
a lot of things.
I see some people that said,
ah, no me, I want
forget about get
rich quick and die
tomorrow is okay.
And their own reason is different.
Yeah, but I'm serving God
because his love for me is
so much and I
can't just help it but respond
to that love.
And that is why I want to
encourage you today that
in this world of evil we
can't really expect explain everything.
Let us not envy the
wicked.
Let us not focus our
attention on the wicked and
their prosperity because
they do prosper.
And let me add quickly on
that, because in our,
in our present day today
there is this
quest of
let me make the money.
Yes, I don't care how I
make the money, let me just have the money.
And that is a
very dangerous place to be
as a child of God.
Because the end now
justifies the means.
Once I have the money, it's
okay even if it's 20 years.
Let me live and die.
I've seen a lot of young
people with that kind of
mindset.
That's not the plan of God for you.
That's not the thought of
God for you.
That's the devil.
And I've seen that
that is so prevalent now.
A lot of people want to make
money, they just don't
care how the money
comes.
And they know the slang in
Nigeria.
Get which get rich quick
or die trying.
Yeah, you know,
that is not the right way
to look at things because
I mean Just try
and go the right way.
That doesn't mean being
Christian you cannot be rich.
No, but you have to do it
the right way.
If at any point
you are inflicting
evil upon others in the
process of trying to get
rich, then that is.
Yeah.
So let's try as much as
possible to do things the right way.
God's way.
That's right.
And that takes us to the
free will defense.
Freeway defense.
What's free will
defense?
We all know what free will is.
Ability to make a choice.
Ability to decide what
you want, to do what
you want at whatever point
in time.
Now, freeway
defense is defined
as the view, the like.
When you say it is the
misuse of
the freeway that God gave
us that led to the
problems we have.
That's free will
defense.
Now, we cannot
totally, completely understand
the problem of evil like
we have been trying to explain.
When we get to heaven, we
know more.
And we are never going to
know everything otherwise
we become another
God.
But when we get to
heaven, we know more.
However, if
you look at it, when God
created man, he gave us
the power to make
a choice.
That's what we refer to
as free will.
And there
is this view that
evil is the result of the
misuse of the
free will that God
gave us.
But that's.
That's the partial truth. Yeah.
People still make right choice.
Yeah.
And they fall into problems.
Yes.
So that will lead
us to the origin of evil
and why evil reigns
on everybody whether you
are righteous or not.
Righteous is
a result of
our roots that has been
corrupted since the
fall in the Garden
of Eden.
But even in that fall,
God still gave us the power
to make a choice.
Now, without free
will, there cannot be
genuine love.
That's an issue because.
Yes, because
some people think that.
Why would God give us the free will?
He should have just made
us to be like.
Yeah, just command us.
Yes.
Follow me.
So you can never go right
or left.
But it's not going to
work like that.
That means you are
forcing, you are being forced
to even love God.
So genuine love cannot
exist without
free will.
So free will,
though it makes evil possible.
Free will makes evil possible
because you don't have the
choice to be
bad if you want to be
bad.
And you have the chance to
be good if you want to be
good, to make a
choice.
But at the same
time, it is also the only
thing that makes possible
any love or goodness
or joy worth
having.
Because you know
that you are in love
with someone
because you want to be,
because it pleases you from
Your heart, you are not
being compelled or
manipulated.
Tools like
today, in this
generation, people
manipulate situations
to be in love with someone,
maybe because of the riches
the person have so that they
can inherit it or whatever.
But that's not true love.
That's not genuine love.
So God does not want
creatures that we love him.
Yes.
Dogmatically,
without the ability to make
a choice.
And that's why he gave us
that free will.
So
if
God had taken away that free
will from us,
then we would be
like slaves.
Yes, we'd be like
slaves who have no
power to,
you know, you can't decide
anything for your
sake.
And the danger in free
will is that when you are
making your choice, whether good
or bad, whether right
or wrong, God is not going
to stop you.
Yes.
And that's where in theology
we said that God took a big risk
because he can.
He allows us to choose
against him,
for him or
without him.
Yeah.
So he wants people that we
voluntarily, genuinely
align with Him.
And that's why he gave us
that choice, so that
we can follow him with true love.
Now let's look at Genesis
2:16
and 17.
Yes.
If you find it, you can.
Otherwise I can read it.
And the Lord God commanded
the man, you are free
to eat from any tree in
the garden, but you must
not eat from.
You must not eat from the
tree of the knowledge of
good and evil.
Okay.
For you.
For when you eat from it,
you will certainly die.
Yes. The law.
God said, it is not good
for the man to be alone.
- That's okay.
My, my.
My version says, you will
die before the end of the day.
Okay.
That is, it's an instant thing.
There's meaning that
once you start the process,
it's no longer reversible.
That's what God is saying.
This one says, if you eat
it, you will die
before the end of
the day.
But unfortunately, we took
that day to be literal.
Something that will happen
instantly, just that day,
but that day.
Human beings were actually
dead from that
moment.
However,
why would God give
that command?
This command further
emphasizes that there was
free will.
Because if there was no free
will, he would not need to
be telling them that if you
do this, this will be the
end result.
If you go the other way,
this will be the end result.
It means there was
free will.
And that was why it was
necessary to
give that
command.
So if you look at that
situation, human beings fail.
Adam and Eve failed because
of the misuse of that
free will.
That is it.
It was because of the misuse.
So God is not to blame.
God is not at fault.
No, never.
It's just like you have a child.
You say, go to school.
You must go to school so
that you will be educated
and you can show your face
wherever others are, you know?
And you refuse to go to school.
It's a free will.
It's a choice.
You can't blame the parent
for not sending the child
to school.
So
like we said, without free
will, we will just be like
machines.
However quickly.
I want us to read a number
of.
Yes, I want.
I want us to read a number
of verses to see
sequentially how this thing unfold.
Deuteronomy 7, 12, 13.
Deuteronomy 7, 12, and 13.
And then, please, next person
should quickly open to
Joshua 24:14.
We read all this quickly,
and then you see how one
thing happens after the other.
Okay?
Deuteronomy 7:12
says, Then
it shall come to pass
because you listen
to these judgments
and keep and do
them that the Lord your God
will keep with
you the covenant and the
mercy which he.
Which he swore to your fathers.
Yeah.
Read the thing as well.
And he will love you
and bless you
and multiply you.
Yes.
He will also bless the
fruit.
The fruit of your
womb and the
fruit of your land.
Yes.
Your grain and
your new wine and your oil.
- Okay, thank you.
- That's okay.
Now look at the first sentence
was that if you
completely obey these
laws, that's a
condition.
So if you completely obey.
So you have a free will
of making your choice.
If you completely obey this
law, these are the blessings
that we follow.
Now let's see.
Joshua 24:14, 15.
Now, fear the Lord and serve
him with all
faithfulness.
Throw away the gods
your ancestors worshiped
beyond the Ephraim river
and in Egypt, and serve the
Lord.
But if serving the Lord
seems undesirable to
you, then choose for
yourselves this day whom
you will serve, whether the
gods your ancestors served
before the Ephraim
or the gods of the
Amorites in whose
land you are living.
But as for me, my
household.
And then what?
What did they say?
How did the Israelites respond?
Then the people answered,
far be it from us to forsake
the Lord to serve all the gods.
Thank you.
So they make a choice.
Okay, so Joshua was telling
them, fear the Lord, follow
his rule.
But if you think that you
want to continue worshiping
the idols that were being
watched where you left,
go ahead.
If you think you don't want
to worship, that this land
was being occupied by the
Amorites before, now they
have their gods.
If
you think that's the
God you want to worship?
Go ahead.
But as for me, in my house,
we worship the Lord.
They made a stand. They made a
choice. They said, okay, we follow you.
They said, we follow you.
Now let's see what happened.
The same people said, we
follow you.
Psalms 81,
Psalm 61.
But no, my people
wouldn't listen.
They would not listen.
Israel did not want me around.
Yes.
So I let them follow their
own stubborn desires.
Living according to their
own desires.
Yes.
Oh, that my people
will listen to me.
Oh, that Israel will
follow me walking in my
path.
How quickly I would
subdue their enemies.
How soon my hands will
be upon their folds.
Okay, so you see, these
are the people said, oh,
we will follow you.
They made a choice, very
clear choice, and God bless them.
They changed their minds.
Then they changed their mind.
They put their free will
through you.
Thank you, our body, soul.
They made you of their
constitutional rights,
called free will.
And then now they
turn against
God.
And so God said, ah, Oh,
I wish you followed me.
Then I will quickly
finish your enemies for you.
But they changed.
They did not follow God.
So we're talking about the
power of free will.
So more or less,
man is the
cause of whatever
consequences he
gets.
Now, finally,
Isaiah 66:4
says,
you refused to
answer when I called
out.
You paid no attention to
my instructions.
Instead, you did what I
hated, not
knowing it was wrong.
So it was a deliberate act.
You knew it was wrong and
you did it.
Now I will punish
you in a
way you dread
the most.
That's God
speaking to his own people
because they made use of
their constitutional right,
free will.
The lesson here is that that
free will still exists
today.
It still exists today.
So you call it amendment.
This amendment, whatever
freeway, has
both sides.
Yes.
It has good
consequences and it
also has bad consequences.
Yes.
So let us use our free will.
Okay.
So.
And you know, so
far we've been looking at
the problem of evil.
And then the big question
came up.
If God is all good and powerful,
why is there a lot of evil?
And then we have established
that the free
will to choose
was there for everyone.
You have the free will to
choose, good or
bad.
But then,
can love and evil
coexist?
That is the question.
When we say evil, how
does evil love comes
into that.
So the lesson here is
telling us that the
free will to
choose between good and
evil was first of all even
born out of God's love towards
us.
He didn't want to force us
to do nothing.
He gave us that free will
because he loves us so much.
He didn't want us to be just
robots that he can just
manipulate all around.
So he gave us the free will
that was his first sign
of love towards us.
So God has granted courage
of free will because it is
necessary for love.
Misuse of this free
will is the cause of evil.
We have established that.
Again, many questions remain.
God allows evil for
a time.
Why passionately despising it?
Because to exclude its
possibility would exclude love.
And to destroy it prematurely
would damage the trust
necessary for love.
He wanted us to trust
him.
And for someone
to love the other person
genuinely, they have to be
able to trust that person.
It's just like myself and
my husband.
There has to be some level
of trust for us to be
this much in love.
So.
So, same thing.
God wants us to trust him.
So you're in love.
Yes, we know.
Okay, so
the exercise of
force is contrary
to the principle of God's government.
God never forces nothing
on us.
He loves us so much, he lets
us exercise our free will.
He desires only the
service of love.
And love cannot be commanded.
Of course, we already know that.
Everybody in love knows that
you cannot force love on someone.
I mean, some people try to
do that, but it's, it's not
going to work.
Yes, all right.
And, and
love cannot be commanded.
It cannot be won by
force or authority.
Only by love is love
awakened.
Yes. To know God is to love him.
His character must be
manifested in contrast to
the character of Satan.
That was something from
desire of ages that lng White
has put out there.
So, but then in all of this,
how do we gain
confidence to trust
in God's goodness?
If there is so much, despite
all this evil happening around
us in the world, how do we
get so much confidence
to trust God's
goodness?
How are we sure that
God's goodness is all is
going to follow us?
They wanted us to read the
book of Romans, chapter 8 and verse 18.
But I want someone to please
open to the book of Revelation,
chapter 21, verse 2 to 3.
Should I read the 18?
Yeah, go ahead and do 8 to
18 as well.
Verse 18.
Eight, 18, yes.
Yet what we suffer now
is, is nothing
compared to the glory he
will reveal to us later.
Amen.
That's it.
So one, we're
gonna go to the next one.
But before then,
whenever we cannot see through
darkness, God can see the
end from the beginning.
It is the end that we're
focusing on.
And according to that book
of Romans, chapter 8, verse
18, the suffering
that we might experience
Right now, because of evil,
that abandoned world, the
suffering, whatever suffering
we might have experienced,
that all might going to,
that we might eventually
end up experiencing does
not compare with the
glory that will be revealed
in us when Jesus
comes the second time.
Let us try and read the book
of Revelation 21,
3 and 4 if you have it.
Revelation.
Okay, I'm there.
It says, and I heard a
loud voice from heaven
saying, behold,
the tabernacle of
God is with
men and
he will dwell with
them and
they shall be his
people.
God himself
will be with them
and will be their God.
Amen.
And God will wipe
away every
fear from their eyes.
There shall be no
more death,
no more
sorrow, nor
crying.
There shall be no
more pain.
No.
For the former things
have all passed away.
Amen.
And that is the conclusion
of the whole matter.
Because eventually
God is going
to bring
is
kingdom here to us.
We're gonna reign with Him.
Eventually there's gonna
be a new heaven and a
new earth.
Whatever it is that we've
suffered on this
planet earth that we consider
as so much evil to
us does not compare to the
glory that is going to come eventually.
And that's what should always
be at the back of our
minds whenever
we remember that there is
so much evil.
And most importantly, this
lesson is also telling us
that God loves us so much
that he sent Jesus Christ
to come and die for us.
That is his love towards us.
He knew this was going to
happen when he gave us the
free will.
But he, he is so
loving as he is, he made
a provision for our salvation.
He made a provision for
redemption.
And that's why I sent Jesus Christ.
So the death of Jesus Christ
on the cross of Calvary is
the fulfillment of
that love again
of God towards we
his own people.
I pray the Lord will bless
us as we continue to have
understanding of this words.
Amen.
The good news is what Dr.
Esther has said,
that there is hope.
Despite the
shortcomings, the
experiences, painful
experiences,
disappointment that you have
had to face difficulties,
poverty, sickness, the death
of your loved ones,
the injustices you have faced.
We are encouraged
to know that
there is hope.
The good news there is that
Jesus will return.
And his returning will
wipe everything
that has cost us pain
before that.
I think that should be
something very confident to you.
Dear brothers and sisters.
On this note we are going
to close this
discussion
as we sing
that to demonstrate that
we continue to love Jesus
until that day
returns.
I love
thee.
In life
I belong
and say
when the
rescue
lies
cold
in my
shots of
glory.
Amen.
I'll sing
with the
little
Jesus is
now
Pastor Jen Pray for us.
Father, thank you for loving
us.
Even though there are many
things we don't understand.
We thank you for
extending your love and mercy
to us.
Please give
us the grace to
trust you more because
we know that you
have the best in mind for us.
This grace we pray
for in Jesus name.
Amen.
Thank you so very much for
studying with us.
Once again there
is hope.
Remember that soon,
and very soon,
Jesus will return.
We encourage you to keep
trusting until then.
God bless.